We have a whole new technology. That's
the most important technology ever. And
you need a whole new infrastructure.
>> Normally when we talk about the
infrastructure world, we're talking
about the servers on the storage and the
network. Here it goes all the way down
to the mines of copper min. That's how
widespread this thing is going to be.
>> It used to be when you built something,
it was an engineering problem. And here
it feels like it really is a resource
limitation. So whether it's tokens or
not, we're pouring a ton of money into
systems and then those systems are
producing a result. And right now we're
bottlenecked on the systems ability to
actually match the resources we're
pouring into them.
>> The leading memory vendor said the
demand they have today will take them 3
years of capacity to supply.
>> If this fund does what we think it will
do, how do we see the world in 5 to 10
years?
>> America wins in the infrastructure
[music] and that would be awesome.
>> Ben Martin Ragu, welcome.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> I want to start with a Mark quote to
introduce this new fund. This is the
biggest technological revolution of my
lifetime. This is clearly bigger than
the internet. The comps on this are the
microprocessor, the steam engine, and
electricity, or maybe the wheel. Guys,
the machine age fund. Please introduce
it. Ben, start us off.
>> Well, um, basically what's uh happened
is we have a whole new technology that's
the most important technology ever. And
what happens every time um there's a
dramatic new way of using all of the
things that we love infrastructure um
you need a whole new infrastructure and
never has it been more high impact as it
is on this one. So not only do we need
new chips, new system software, we need
new ways of doing power, we need to
replace copper. I [laughter] mean like
it's absolutely everything. So it's a
very exciting time. So you know
particularly for the kind of hardware
aspects of of this new era um we needed
a new approach.
>> Yeah I would agree. I mean normally when
we at least in the computing when we
talk about the infrastructure world we
talking about the servers and the
storage in the network here it goes all
the way down to the mines copper mines.
That's how widespread this thing is
going to be.
Um that's number one and number two I
think what we have seen over the last 3
years is the steady increase of the
capabilities of the models where the
model is no longer the bottleneck and in
fact using AI these models are getting
better faster and faster and faster. Now
the bottleneck is all what I call south
of the model and so that's why we need
to work on that. You know, the only
thing I'd add very quickly is like we
tend to follow founders and we've been
watching over the last couple of years
is the number of very strong teams going
after complex hardware problems has
increased. I don't know the actual
numbers but I was trying to estimate it
over the weekend. So I think we'd get
you maybe 5% of the deals from top
founders would come in would be hardwood
before. Now I would say north of 20% or
30% right now. So like the founder
community which tends to be much smarter
than the VC community has identified
this as a very active area for
innovation and they're responding. I
think 5% is probably generous.
>> Yeah, it's very low. Is very low. Yeah.
3%. Yeah.
>> And explain some of the macro conditions
that have led to this this trans this
change in terms of the surplus of
founders pursuing these idea. Like what
are they seeing that's that's enabled?
>> Well, I mean the obvious is like you
know the the demand for AI is basically
infinite and as a result of that every
part of the supply chain is under under
duress. I mean everything including like
materials used to make things like like
memory. Um it's also very interesting
whether there's something unique about
AI. Um which because the demand is
infinite and growth is infinite. Um uh
what you tend to worry about is the
margin of companies which is how
efficient it is. Like normally you worry
about growth like can I just you know
can I just get people to buy this stuff.
You don't have to worry about that here.
The question is is can you do this in a
way that's profitable? And a lot of the
um efficiencies are actually strictly
[snorts] a physical limitation of
hardware. And so even the business model
of the AI wave is really putting a lot
of stress on the existing systems
because they weren't built for AI. They
weren't built for those workloads. And I
think there's just this you know this
global observation that we actually need
to change the core components to get
that efficiency to help drive the growth
and to drive the value of the
businesses.
>> Yeah. And how did [clears throat] we
know that demand is actually outpacing
supply here rather than this being you
know another hype cycle? Well,
[laughter] I mean,
>> yeah, there are any number of cities
today. Um, firstly, it is that some of
the smartest judges of demand are
cutting huge purchase orders. I mean, if
you look at the hyperscalers, right?
>> Yeah.
>> Their capex spend has been exploding.
Next year supposedly, it's going to
reach a trillion dollars collectively
across the big hyperscalers. This year,
it's about 700 billion dollars, right?
And if you think about the hyperscalers
position in the industry, they see
demand from everywhere, right? They see
obviously the frontier labs um wanting
their compute, they see the AI native
companies, they see the enterprise, they
see the US geography, the international
geography. So if anybody has visibility,
it is down and they've been jacking up
their capex like it's never been seen
before, right? So that's a clear clear
sign. And secondly, if you look at the
companies that we see on a day-to-day
basis, they are all ripping. All the
application companies, the growth is
insane. The frontier labs, the growth is
insane. It's been documented. So I would
say on the demand side, the signals have
never been clearer that this is not a
hype. It's to top it all, all of it is
just and prices are going up.
>> Like we've never seen prices go like up
on chips.
>> You keep your prices went down. They
always go down. Yeah. It always goes
down. If you look at the price curve, it
it went like this and then went back
this.
>> Yeah.
>> And we know only like 5 10% of the
address for the market to stop today.
>> I mean, the the the supply, if you look,
if you look at the supply across the
board, it's basically all booked out to
2028.
I mean, it's so bad we've actually seen
multi-day auctions for a few thousand
GPUs.
Um, you know, the other side of that, of
course, is demand. And as Ragu said,
we've seen the fastest growing companies
we've seen in the history of the
industry.
>> But also the unit of work that AI can
do,
the value of that unit of work keeps
increasing. But underneath the covers,
the number of tokens that are consumed
is going by orders of magnitude, right?
If it's one token for I mean 100 tokens
for chat or an agent, it's thousands of
tokens, right? So you got expansion of
both sides of demand. One is the unit of
work is becoming more and more
consumptive
>> of tokens and then secondly the number
of people therefore that are going to be
benefit it's not just the developers
it's going to be all knowledge workers
and then all of beyond that so that's
that's what we see
>> you said the key components in supply
are sold out to 2027 maybe in 2028
>> what does it mean for an entire industry
to be sold out that that far like
>> I don't know this has ever happened
before do you guys recall I mean
remember in the Um, in in in the
internet days when we were doing massive
buildout, the majority that was actually
being put in the ground was speculative
and was dark. Remember the dark fiber?
And here basically every GPU that's
being created is already pre-sold. So
>> yeah, we weren't quite there. I mean
there was
there was a lack of bandwidth
like in the 989 time frame, but
there wasn't there there wasn't that
much real demand for it because there
just weren't that many people on the
internet. So like it was a two-sided
thing and the companies were all rushing
there and needed more bandwidth
theoretically, but there weren't
the users on the other side to consume
it necessarily. And then to really
consume a lot of bandwidth, you have to
do high bandwidth things like video,
which weren't really viable for, you
know, a number of reasons that that had
nothing to do with how much bandwidth
was in the data center. So it smelled
similar, but it wasn't this. This is
like we're flat out and people are
reselling GPUs for four times what they
bought them for and this kind of thing.
Like it's just not. And then,
>> you know, we're we're also out of power
and cooling. Uh and then on top of that,
it's really hard to build because
there's these incredible political
headwinds going into it. So, it's it's
really unprecedented in my career. uh
that we've had anything anything like
this. No,
>> I want to give you a quick anecdote. So,
this I was talking to a CFO of a large
company, large public company who had
historically been very resistant about
going into the cloud. So, they had a lot
of servers and they were doing an
inventory uh check and they realized
that the memory in their servers had
increased so much it could uh fund the
entire migration to the cloud. So, I
just feel like we're in a very unusual
situation.
>> Yeah, [laughter] that's right. We're out
of many things. power, cooling, memory,
GPUs, like you name it, we're out of it.
>> Yeah. So, the flagship uh conference for
the industry is the one called hot chips
is going on in Stanford and the leading
memory vendor said the demand they have
today it will take them 3 years of
capacity to supply it. It's just today
it's not even future demand.
So in terms of being about everything
simultaneously, is it because people
just underestimated how good the models
would be, how how useful they would be,
they just couldn't have foreseen the
demand?
>> Well, I don't even think it's that. I
mean, this stuff came out of nowhere,
right? We we're only four years into
this. So even if we had a perfect
oracle, once it started working, I don't
think
>> we could have built the capacity.
>> We could have built the capacity.
There's no way. And we're talking about
like chip cycles, which tend to be three
to four years. We're talking about
breaking ground and building data
centers which is you know four to five
years we're talking
>> and connecting breaking down and
building them and having uh power
source. So like you either have to build
your own power or like usually both
you've got to build your own power and
have a power source which is not easy.
Yeah. the ML industry that's used if
it's growing at 20 30% it's a great
growth rate right and it's being
connected to an AI software industry
that's like triple digits is the base
you know
>> so you can see the disconnect right so
it's it's just wide bank
>> and so why didn't this fund exist you
know five years ago or seven years ago
or why was it not a great category to to
invest in in in the same way Brad
>> well I would say we're probably I'd like
to think for just in time, but you know,
we probably would have been uh well
suited to have it at least a couple
years ago.
>> I will say you could actually point on
on on basically every epoch to uh an
independent company that came up, right?
Clearly the move from the client from uh
in mainframe to the client server, we
saw a bunch of companies come up. Um the
move to the internet, this we got Cisco
and Juniper. uh even in the mega data
centers which by the way was largely
driven by the incumbent cloud providers
verticalizing you saw the uh arising of
Arista so there has been the ability to
invest in you know silicon and hardware
but it's been relatively minor because
the change has been relatively minor
like one chip company one switch company
where here everything is and so I I
agree with Ben we're probably you know
we probably could have started a little
bit earlier um but the amount of change
is so high now that it's just an obvious
thing
And the other thing is the demand for
intelligence is so vertical um with
really no end in sight. I mean cuz every
company that's adopted it is growing
very fast in its usage and then most
companies haven't adopted it to a high
degree and then consumers are just
getting started.
And so it's going to probably the demand
for tokens is probably going to grow
close to a,000% a year, which you cannot
grow supply that fast. Like like we're
not
>> like the amount of just work we're going
to have to do across the board to get to
the point where we can grow like infr at
that kind of rate is is pretty vast. So
I think there's a lot of investing
opportunity on the way. And by the way,
the other thing is like all the
architectures
of the hardware systems were built for a
whole different era of computing. And so
more than just we need more capacity, we
need capacity to build there there's
lots of opportunities to build different
kinds of infrastructure. Yeah, they're
they're all reaching their the physics
limits for what they were designed,
right? Like what Ben was talking about
copper and so on and so forth. And you
could go across every one of these
categories and you could find, okay,
this is the limit of this type of
technology. So now you got to get some
technical breakthroughs to get to the
next one.
>> Yeah. I want to dive deeper on the
demand side for a second. As we've moved
from chat bots to reasoning to agents to
to multi- aents, each step has
multiplied the number of tokens a single
task takes up by orders of increasing
orders.
>> Yeah, nobody likes to use AI more than
AI. [laughter]
>> So, um why does that keep happening
instead of a leveling off? Do you just
see that happening you know indefinitely
just continuing to
>> uh well so there's a couple as that the
first one is is for sure right now if
you look at like the the way we're
achieving scaling the way we're doing it
is through a lot of inference so through
a lot of token right if you think about
what RL is you know it's it's a lot of
inference if you think about chain of
thought it's a lot of inference u think
longunning agents of course it's a lot
of inference and so that's just
basically been one of the approaches
that we've been using to um uh to
scaling um I think if you want to step
back and say kind of what is the macro
trend here it used to be when you built
something it was an engineering problem
and you throw a bunch of engineers at it
and that doesn't scale and that would
have a natural law of engineering
physics uh which is what the mythical
manmouth came from and here it feels
like it really is a resource limitation
so whether it's tokens or not we're
pouring a ton of money into systems and
then those systems are producing a
result and right now we're bottlenecked
on those position those systems ability
to actually uh match the resources we're
pouring into them. And so I think like
tokens right now is probably where we
are on the scaling curve, but we don't
have a natural regulator like
engineering like we did before. So I
think we should expect this to continue
and we have to build a supply to support
it.
>> Yeah. Like the simple way to think about
it is
any problem that you have can be solved
with enough
infrastructure [laughter]
>> basically
>> GPUs and power and money. Uh and so
until we run out of problems, we're not
going to run out of demand. And that's
the that's the uh challenge. I
>> mean AI's answer to getting better and
better is to use more AI, right?
inference is one basic building block
that it keeps using over and over and
over again and so that's why these
tokens multiply at each step.
>> Yeah, even the autoc catalytic effect so
even the idea of using AI to create more
AI like creating a GPU kernel of course
is just using more AI um as part of the
process. So again, one way that we think
about it is in the past money would come
in, you have an engineering problem, we
know that it takes two years, normally
fails, you know, it's a national
governor and then you get the product on
the other end. This there's there's
there's nothing between the money going
in and then the hardware, you know,
creating intelligence. And so now we're
just limited by our ability to create
supply. It's a very very different
>> be more GPUs and our sol.
>> Yeah, that's right.
>> So that's the cycle. as long as you have
the money, the GPUs, and the data, you
know, for the foreseeable future, you'll
be able to scale these things.
>> And it's it's fascinating because, you
know, over the last decade, it feels
like there so many, you know, people and
the pervasive sentiment was there's too
much money going to startups. We're
overfunding these startups. There's too
much money in in in in venture capital.
Say more Ben about what that means
because there there used to be this um
sort of skepticism that the more money
you put into into the industry that you
know there would be bigger outcomes and
now you know we were saying at the
offsite that there's to some degree the
the market is as big as we collectively
contribute to it.
>> Yeah. So, this is this look, the one
thing we all knew with in startup world
is that if I have a two-year lead on you
and you try and catch me by hiring a
thousand engineers, you're going to
wreck your company. Like, that never
works. It's a mythical man month. Nine
women can't have a baby in a month. That
like that's it. Like, that never works.
Okay, now that works. [laughter]
But it's not hiring a hundred thousand
engineers. It's taking $3 billion
and like lighting up a magnificent
cluster and then all of a sudden, you
know, whatever Grock can come out of
nowhere and like, oh, all of a sudden
it's real or or a Kimmy or or what have
you.
It's just like these leads um you can
throw money at the problem and you can
throw money at almost any problem and
that works. And so that is just
completely different than anything we've
ever lived through. So we're, by the
way, we're all psychologically adjusting
to this. The Chad GBT app has a billion
weekly activives. There's about 30
million uh developers um who are using,
you know, relatively a big portion of
compute demands. How do we think about
compute compute demands needs now and in
the future in light of what people are
actually doing with AI?
>> That's the progression, right? So Chadic
was a casual app and it's coding for
professionals right now using coding you
have now built amazing tools for
knowledge workers so that's the next
frontier and now there are over a
billion knowledge workers in the line
right and with that it's a long ways to
go for that demand and by the way the
work that they do all this workflow and
automation and so on and then you get to
the back office which is all the agents
So progressively each of these things
unlocks
uh I would say order of magnitude more
demand. I mean just at the start of this
>> well and now you have Grockbot which is
kind of uh you know what uh happened
with coding is kind of happening with
all use of computer viaot and so we're
in a whole another wave of demand and
most certainly there's going to be more
to come. Uh so it does seem quite
unlimited at the moment and we haven't
even gotten into embodied AI or robots
uh which are going to be another source
of demand.
>> Martinez is expert but my understanding
is that part uses computer use which is
just like
>> human being sitting inside the computer
typing away.
>> I literally used it over the weekend to
to update my credit card with a bunch of
services that I'd been like lazy to do
and cancel a bunch of subscriptions. I
mean, this is not coding or whatever.
This is true computer use.
>> All of a sudden, you're creating like
half a billion knowledge workers except
they're all sitting inside of the
computer [laughter]
doing what?
>> I I do I do think that that that Mark
Mark Andre is right. It's like the right
analog here is like the steam engine or
electricity in the following way. Like
we've we've introduced this new thing
that you can turn to work and there are
some very obvious applications now, but
there's probably 30 40 years of throwing
computer at problems. anything with a
clear reward signal and we we're just
starting like we've got language and
code that's it and just starting
computer use but like what else are we
looking at we're looking at uh in terms
of science materials biology I mean of
course creativity is a massive use and
so listen we're at the very very early
part of a very long journey and we've
removed this key bottleneck which is you
know traditional software engineering
now of course you know bottlenecks will
move and there'll be kind of more
complexity elsewhere but I think we're
at a very early in a very long run of
throwing computer problem. So let's
expect you know this compute need to
persist for decades.
>> But because we mentioned it u Marty talk
about grabbot um because we um we're
talking at the offsite about how you
know what what struck you about it.
Obviously we're involved in every
possible way you could you could be
involved but what um yeah what what did
you find so interesting about it? So I
think we've I think we've as an industry
gone through kind of multiple
realizations for how AI enters our
lives, right? And and uh very early on
we're like okay well you add AI to a
product and it's like whatever it's like
a search bar and then you kind of you
know you you do chat with it and it
chats back because that's kind of the
traditional way to do it. Um uh and then
Open Clock kind of showed up and that
was it earlier in the year. And with
Open I say, "Okay, well maybe like it
just being like Google but better. Maybe
that's not the full embodiment of it.
How about we'll have it be a standalone
thing but it'll be an extension of you
and it'll share your keys and it'll know
your passwords and it'll just kind of do
stuff that you would do, right? So it's
kind of an extension of you but it's
more like a human, an extension of you."
And then [snorts] what I think Rockbot
got really right is no, how about it's
actually an employee. So now you have
this thing that's an entity and it
doesn't have like special access to your
keys or whatever. It has its own
computer and it has its own browser and
because these are the smartest models in
the world, it can do whatever an
employee can do. And it's kind of
interesting because now actually if I if
I want something done my first thing I I
think is like well can do it for me and
and often the answer is yes even if it's
something you wouldn't you know expect
it. So, the obvious ones are like
whatever. It'll like manage my calendar.
It'll like book a meeting, but there's
also non-obvious ones as well. Like, so,
for example, I'll have it um uh read
through my email and do triage. And and
I did I don't tell it how to do that,
but it will know to check with me before
actually doing the triage. So, like
these things are sophisticated enough
that you can give a relatively high
level task and it'll do kind of, you
know, like sophisticated things as a
result.
>> Ben, I know you're thinking a lot a lot
about this and how this you know, works
in the organization. you think a lot
about culture of course. What are your
thoughts here?
Well, I mean, I think if you just look
at us, um,
you know, it's like having a new kind of
employee and
there's going to be a lot of them and we
have to just like, you know, with our we
spent many, many, many years figuring
out how to work with our kind of regular
human employees and now we've got these
other kinds of employees
and, you know, there is a learning curve
with them. So um they can burn a lot of
tokens and spend a lot of money and get
nothing productive done. Um they can
forget stuff. They can make stuff up. Um
you know they can have good behavior.
They can have bad behavior. They can
>> they can create security problems. So
like there there there's all those
aspects to it, but like they can also be
like super duper productive. And so I
think figuring out how to integrate them
in, have them work nicely with the
people that they're working with, um,
the actual humans, uh, is all something
that we're learning how to do. I mean, I
I don't want to sit up here and say I've
cracked the code. We've got this more of
a sloop and [laughter] the whole firm is
just completely automated now, and I'm
going to slowly get rid of all the
humans because I can. Like, that's not
at all where we are. were much more
going like, okay, how do we make all our
humans superhuman um without like
wrecking the place um because the bots
got out of control?
>> Yeah. And it's interesting because we've
done we've tried a couple of different
ways as how best to get agents into the
system if you will and eventually
it was Martin's insights just treat them
as people and get it done. And that's
what we're doing. that's turned out to
be the most durable way of getting this
thing going inside of an organization.
>> I want to go back to the supply side and
go deeper into the the bottlenecks. You
we were talking about how you know in
terms of the data centers, the chip
architecture, system software,
facilities themselves that none of them
were designed with with AI in mind. What
would it look like for them to be
designed with AI? Like what is sort of
the mental model for thinking about what
that could mean?
>> Yeah. So um I mean if you
start with a statement that you just say
hey original model
um of infrastructure on any of these
models has to change you can go se
category by column and see how it bricks
right and then you start uh unlocking
the bottlenecks in each one of these
things. So eventually you have to get to
a system where if you look at what an
inference engine does, right? It takes
up a lot of memory, it generates new
tokens along with the compute. And so
you can just think about how do I
optimize all of this? What does the
memory need to be? What does the compute
need to be? How do they need to talk to
each other? How much power does each of
them need? And if they need all of these
power, how do you cool each of these?
Right? And then how do you put the
collections of these things together?
That is the exercise that's underway in
the industry right now with a lot of the
founders. So they're breaking down the
problem into its fundamental components
and saying what is the exact nature of
the compute that's getting done. Okay,
it's how it's going to be matrix
multiplications. How do I optimize my
compute around that kind of a scenario
and then they all need very
progressively to generate these tokens?
What is the best way of hierarchically
arranging this memory right and then how
does the power consume I mean then you
got to connect it together what are the
ways of connecting it on the same chip
but across chips and across data centers
how much power does each of these data
transmission take so you have to
progressively break it all down and
rebuild it from these fundamental
building blocks and that's what we see
underway and that's where we see the
opportunity
>> let me give you an interesting mental
model to think about how the landscape's
changed so um uh so today to build a
frontier model costs let's say $3 to5
billion right so and let's you know and
and that's to train it and so the
inference has to pay back at least that
of course right you know in order for
any of this stuff to be viable let's say
two times that so let's say that now
inferred has to to make $10 billion so
if you can save 20% of efficiency on
that that's $2 billion and you can
easily build an ASIC for $2 billion
Right. So, so we've actually gotten to
this interesting point in the industry
where it actually makes sense to build
an ASIC per model just because the
amount of capital investment in that
model and then unlike traditional
software, traditional software has a lot
of state and a lot of you know is very
dynamic. These models are fixed. The
model weights are fixed. And so we don't
know if the world goes to per model A6.
But it gives you a great mental model of
how you would evolve the architecture to
be far more bespoke for these massive
capital investments we're doing. Like I
don't think in the history of the
industry we've ever created a digital
artifact with something like $5 billion
that went directly into that artifact.
And so you know like this I think is
going to put the greatest demands on
hardware that we've ever seen. Well, to
that end, rack power requirements are
moving from roughly 5 to 10 kilowatts to
100 to 50 kilowatts. Compute density is
climbing something like 70x.
>> Cooling is moving from air to liquid as
a requirement. What are the investment
opportunities as a result of this?
>> Well, first of all, when you get to that
level of power per rack, AC power
doesn't work anymore. [laughter] So,
like that's a pretty wild thing. Um, so
now now you're into DC power, which by
the way also requires its own cooling.
Um, and is like,
uh, by the way, super dangerous.
Uh,
which is kind of ironic because this
was, um, Edison promoted DC power by
claiming how dangerous AC power was in
demonstrating it [laughter] by like
electrocuting animals and things.
>> The horse. Yeah.
So but he was right but around his own
kind of power which is extremely
powerful is the good news. Um so you
know just starting with power uh yeah
that's going to be like very very
different I think with cooling. So and
this gets into
so yes we're going air cooling to liquid
cooling. I think we're already at liquid
cooling for any state-of-the-art data
center. Like that's already kind of a
done thing.
>> But it gets into okay, you know, given
the political environment and so forth,
you like liquid cooling isn't enough.
It's got to be eco-friendly liquid
cooling. Um, and you know, kind of DC
power is not enough. It's got to be um
power that contributes uh to the power
of society, not takes away from it. And
so you have data centers who have been
behaving badly. Um small percentage
actually probably 10%
wasting a lot of water. Um you know not
as much as pistachios or almonds and so
forth as people demonstrate on the
internet but like they could be a lot
more efficient with that. Uh and then
there are ones that you know kind of are
uh parasites of power and don't
contribute power back. I think all
that's going to end. it's going to have
to end just because like like that we
we've kind of gone through a one-way
door on that. Uh so that requires like a
level of engineering um that you know
many haven't invested in yet. So that's
coming. Uh and then you know like if
racks are that dense um there are other
things that like the way the floors are
designed have to support that kind of
weight. uh you know that kind of thing
is is actually for real. Um and then you
know I I think that there's
you know you just need a lot of
everything and so there's going to be
you know kind also by the things are
really loud so you have to build the
data center with thicker walls or you're
going to disturb the peace in the
neighborhood which is not going to be
acceptable like I don't think any
state's going to allow that.
>> And so a lot of the ways people have
architected and designed
the buildings themselves are already
completely obsolete. Like once we get to
Fineman, um a much smaller percentage of
the data centers that we have today
work. In fact, I mean everybody talks
about memory prices, but one of the
fastest areas where prices is increasing
is reinforced concrete from for their
sake.
>> The other thing that happens when these
data centers are uh sending 800 volts to
the whack is it's become so dangerous
number one, but secondly, we don't have
enough electrical contractors that have
the expertise to deal with the 800 rules
inside the data center. because this is
high voltage. Only 2% of electrical
engineer or uh electricians in the US
have been certified on DC power. So like
that gives you an idea. Now Meta's got a
whole program to train people up and so
forth which is great. It's like a new
job court where they train people for
free to do this job. But you know it's
funny AI is taking all the jobs. AI is
going to create a lot of new
electricians.
>> Yeah. I think we're just doing something
in space too. the big guys that own the
big cloud data big data centers, they
all are furiously experimenting with the
robots, right? To do the work of
assembling or putting servers into the
data center, etc. And so you will see
that increasing as a result of the
evolution in AI.
>> By the way, to be to be clear on the um
on the actual fund that we're raising,
our focus is on computer science
infrastructure. So anything a model runs
on that's computer science right so
think you know chips network
interconnect storage all the way down
probably to the electricity
>> yeah and and saying more about the
robotics arm in terms of what we'll be
doing versus maybe American dynamism or
how to think about that
>> yeah yeah for sure so um you know again
we we think that any platform that that
AI will run on like one of the the the
great breakthroughs that AI does is it
allows computers to interact with the
physical world, right? It can see, it
can hear, it can talk, right? And this
means new platforms, right? And the
simplest way people say edge device, but
that doesn't really mean anything,
right? I mean, it could be a mobile
device, it could be a CDN, it could be a
laptop, but it also could be an
embodied, you know, device that goes
around. And so again, we we um as you
know, as infrastructure focused
investors don't do heavy regulated
industries um or more verticalized
industries, but any sort of computer
science platform that's going to push AI
further out, we're quite interested in.
>> Yeah. Going back to the data centers, by
2028, new data centers are going to need
something like 44 gawatts of additional
power against maybe 25 gawatt of
expected grid additions.
>> Hold on, hold on. We use that word
gigawatt.
>> No, it's like it's like we'll have 100
gigawatt, [laughter]
>> Martine. What's a gigawatt?
>> I mean I mean how big is it? It's
multiple football fields. I mean it's
massive. It's 50,000 50,000 people.
>> What do you mean? What is it?
>> Like like
>> the equivalent is like 50,000 houses.
>> City
>> 50,000 50,000 homes. 50,000 homes.
I I I grew up I grew up in Flagstaff,
Arizona, [laughter]
which is a town of 40 to 60,000 people,
depending on the universities. We have
less than a gigawatt of power
consumption. I mean, this is
>> so you can basically light up and air
condition your entire town for a
gigawatt.
>> Yeah. I mean, this is
>> just throwing them around. [laughter]
>> No, but by the way, everybody talks
about the gigawatt. There's very few
gigawatt data centers that are actually
up. I mean, we've got a long way to go,
right? But then why can't utilities and
hyperscalers just build faster?
Oh, there's so many things there. Well,
there's first of all, right now, you
need humans to build them. So, there
there's just like the regular
construction, but much more than that,
you need
permits.
Um, you need access to power uh that you
can plug in. So you're either you're
doing a combination of you've got to get
access to power which is a massive kind
of regulatory
bidding struggle. There's very limited
kind of amounts and things you can tap
into in terms of n natural gas power
grids, what have you. Um but then you
also have to build your own power and
guess what? We've got shortages of
transformers and turbines and everything
that goes into that. So, it's just,
you know, like you've got to get all
that stuff. It's not this is not a
software problem. It's not just like a
bunch of engineers can't you like work
weekends and that type of stuff like
this is not that that works anyway, but
uh
there are real bottlenecks in this and
these these lead times are not that easy
to compress. And look, we have the best
minds in the world trying to figure out
how to compress them. Uh but
I it's not easy. It's not easy and the
demand is not slowing down. So we're
already behind. The demand is growing,
you know, 10x a year right now. And you
the supply just can't grow that fast.
>> By the way, it is so bad that right now
if we have new companies going for GPUs,
it's often in Mexico or Australia or
another country just because it is so
difficult in the United States. Yeah,
we're creating huge both job and
long-term economic opportunity in other
countries by uh banning data centers
here. I think look the the right answer
would be to set a standard where a data
center contributes
back to the community like that power
gets better, there's no noise, there's
no water issue, um and it's adding jobs
like that ought to be the standard.
Yeah. And then everybody ought to be
just held to that center. And by the
way, like there are there are data
centers that do that now. Like that's
not a you know like a a futuristic dream
or something. Rates energy rates have
gone down like every year they're there.
And the reason is they provide their own
power. They give power to to the state
during the day and then at night they
borrow power from the state when the
state doesn't need it because you're
always the the way power plants work is
you're always generating peak uh
capacity and since a data center has
steady capacity during day and night and
a city goes way up in the day and way
down at night um that's a symbiotic
relationship. zooming out. Uh why do we
think the you know we we've been batting
around the name for for a little bit. Uh
why do we think machine age is a is a
compelling term for for what we're doing
here?
>> Well, listen, let let me let me take it.
So, the first one is I think Ben's
absolutely right. Artificial
intelligence was the wrong word. Like we
shouldn't have called it it's machine
intelligence. Um
>> say more about that. Why is that?
>> Uh because it's not how humans think
necessarily, right? I mean, it is a
cache of how humans thought is a
collection of humans thoughts. But like
to date, we don't know how to take a um
an AI with no knowledge and put it in
out in the world and have it reconstruct
language, right? Like that's not what
we've done, right? We've we've built a
something that can learn off of
everything we've already learned and
then use that in a productive way. And
listen, a a AI is a general term that
goes back 70 years in computer science
formally that applies to many different
things. And of course it's got a lot of
baggage either from science fiction or
from you know Nick Bstrom who wrote
about it or whatever. And so so the
first one is just an acknowledgement
like this really is machine
intelligence. And then you want to
emphasize the machine part of it. I mean
there's kind of this deep irony and this
is from you know the uh the software's
eating the world people that you know
you've really come to a place where you
pour money into something and then
you're limited by the actual machines
below it. And so I think it is a kind of
a nod to like the hardware component is
so significant in this wave and and we
want to acknowledge that.
>> Yeah. I think that's what's going to
create the next breakthroughs in
intelligence is the quality of the
machines underneath. And so that's
that's basically a reason for the name.
>> It's also a cool name. [laughter]
>> That sounds good.
>> Futuristic.
>> Yeah. the um given how much has been
spent on AI infrastructure to date and
how capex intensive these businesses can
be are we past the point where new
companies can break break in at at at
sort of material levels uh you know you
know in why not incumbents like Nvidia
Core etc just take the line share of
these markets
they're all doing well there's no
question about it right but to our
discussion earlier when you're get you
need funly new innovations to keep the
growth both continuing or the pace of
improvement continuing whether it's
tokens per second per dollar or tokens
per watt
uh tokens per rack right um or power you
take any metric if you want to have a
10x on those metrics you got to have new
innovation and new innovation
traditionally comes from brilliant
founders thinking about solving the
problem from first principles in a
different way right and that's what's
needed here for the next jump in
innovation.
>> I mean this is the law of markets,
right? I mean let's assume that the the
existing silicon incumbents are multi-
trillion dollars in market cap which is
absolutely the case.
>> Even
5% of that is a massive private company,
massive private company, right? We're
talking, you know, annual. Um and you
could say, well, but Nvidia could do
that. They could, but why would they if
they're focused on things that are in
the 90% which is also driving the same
amount of growth? You always ask these
questions. We ask these questions during
the cloud days, right? Like why wouldn't
Amazon did this? You would ask these
questions during the Microsoft days. Why
wouldn't Microsoft do this? There's a
very natural law of markets is once you
get to a certain scale, there's
tremendous opportunity for innovation um
at at the margins.
>> Yeah, there's a funny uh quote from our
partner Alex Rmpelle. He had this
startup called Trial Pay and he was
trying to sell it to or sell the it his
services to to Meta and uh then Facebook
and Dan Rose who was the head of corp
dev at the time said Alex that's great
you're it sounds like you can collect a
lot of silver bricks but I'm like I have
so many gold bricks I can't even pick
them all up so the last thing I'm doing
is looking at a silver brick and I think
Nvidia is in that position
>> 100% yeah we were talking about as
relates to the model providers that if
you're, you know, in the sweet spot of
of what open airropic can can do, you
know, one of their main sort of interest
areas, that might be a tough place to
be, but anything outside of those maybe,
you know, three to five areas might uh,
you know, as as markets expand, they
fragment, right? And it happens all the
time. And remember in the early days of
Ford, there was the 1913, there was the
Rouge River plant. Literally this, you
know, this was like made cars like in
went like water, coal, and rubber trees
and out came cars.
>> By the way, he bought a whole
>> rubber
plantation in the Amazon jungle,
>> right? And and there's a great book
called Ford Landia where so because he
wanted to like own like the complete
vertical thing where he created this
city called Ford Landia in the Amazon
jungle um which had like was all
Americanized band stands and ice cream
and all this kind of stuff. And it
actually worked for a while until uh he
made people like show up to things on
time and then they were like screw this
get the out of here. [laughter]
So, so now if you look at the car
industry, of course, there's multiple
levels of supplier and there's a bunch
of companies and this always happens.
So, you know, as markets expand, they
fragment. There's a lot of and then and
then once that growth slows down, they
tend to consolidate. The consolidation
can either be acquisition or it can be
like new challengers rise up and that
that is the, you know, everlasting cycle
of private markets.
>> Yeah. the use cases are are multiplying
and there's no way like if you're the
biggest company you can get to the
biggest use cases but there's so many
use cases and all as Martin was saying
very valuable use cases that it's just
very hard to get to in a great way
>> yeah even inference used to be one
simple architecture right and it no
longer is like it's so complex now so
it's inevitable that you can optimize
things in a different way
>> by the way here's a very interesting
thing like people don't um uh often
don't understand that like the margins
kind of fell out of the standard way of
doing the technology with software,
right? Like it wasn't really a
technology problem. Like once you got
the business working, you tended to have
pretty good margins because that's just
kind of how software works. certainly
when you shipped it but even as a
service uh and that's not necessarily
the case with AIS we may actually be
entering an era where the optimization
in the hardware is absolutely meaningful
to the upside of the business in a way
that we haven't seen in the past so
there's a lot of opportunity here let's
get deeper in talking about the types of
companies we'll be investing in um maybe
we could start by either illustrating
the the the subsectors or if we can talk
about a few um or a couple investments
that we've I know there's some that
haven't been announced yet, but Robert,
do you want to take us down?
>> Yeah, I mean the sub sectors as we've
been talking all is every one of these
categories, right? The obvious ones are
um uh computer chips, but these days
it's not enough to build a chip. You
need to build a full system, right? And
then therefore, what goes into the
system? There's potentially memory
innovation. There is potentially
networking innovation. There's
potentially power chips and so on and so
forth. So each one of these categories
are categories where you can see public
company style companies emerging and
those are all things that we are looking
into. Um and then once you put it all
together there's a layer of software
around it to automate all of these
things to manage these fleets and so on
and so forth. So that is another
important area. So these things keep
building on each other but every one of
these categories is important.
>> Talk about what's different about these
kinds of companies from from the usual
company. I mean one thing you can tell
from the companies we announced is their
first rounds have been massive. You know
hundreds of millions. Is it a different
kind of founder or what else is
different as we think about just the
practice of you know building and
investing these kinds of businesses
relative to our traditional software?
>> Well I I think the big thing is you hit
on one of the big things which is a lot
of money goes in um before they get to a
product. Um and that's just kind of the
nature of it. Now that's true on big
models too, but I I would say
that's a little more of a known path. Uh
whereas this has got a little more risk
and a little more money than uh than
some of the other things that we've
done. But
>> um and you know, look, a lot of a lot of
the chip founders um are here from the
past.
>> You know, like the guys who know how to
make memory, [snorts] they're not young.
Yeah, [laughter]
you know, so it's uh you know that part
is different too, but it's kind of
exciting, you know.
>> Yeah. The other thing about these
founders,
they have all got to be
systems founders. So what I mean by that
is you can't just be a researcher or a
great computer scientist, right? You got
to be able to architect and design the
chip or the system, whatever it is. Then
you got to think about how is this thing
going to actually get manufactured,
right? who's going to be supplying this
and a whole bunch of these downstream
things which normally if you're building
software you don't have to think about
all of these things. So the to really
the best founders um
and of course Jensen is the Michael
Jordan of this right they think the
entire ecosystem right from the get- go
before they start designing the chain
right because of the nature of the
bottlenecks and all these things that
have to come together. So that's that's
a big characteristic that is different.
>> There there's two environmental factors
that are important too. The first one is
the labs are so desperate that they will
engage with startups. And so like we
actually have quite a bit of signal
early on because they're you labs are
inking deals with companies before they
actually have hardware available. And
that's a big big shift than you know 5
years ago, right? Like you just didn't
go and you know sell your kind of janky
hardware thing to Google or whatever. So
that that's a shift. The second one is
the the capital availability has
loosened up a lot. I think there's
general consensus that that you know it
is the time that to reshape this stuff
and so follow on rounds there's a lot of
capital available which you know of
course you want to be investing into
areas where there's capital available
and so the atmospherics are also just
different. Patrick Carlson, you know,
remarked a few years ago said, "Hey, it
feels like there's less younger founders
today, you know, in the way that you
know, Zuck, you know, in college
building next Facebook or or Gates, um,
you know, in the same way with Microsoft
and of course, you know, the Michael
Trolls of the world, there there's
still, you know, some young founders
building iconic companies, but it does
seem, you know, to your point that
there's more older founders building
these these these companies or or less
20-year-olds. I'm I'm curious if you
resonates and why. Well, I think it's
Ragu's point that if
if you're building something that has
like a very complicated supply chain,
has to manufacture things um and is
technically complicated that you know
some experience helps uh and you know if
you look at Elon or Travis Kalanick
their companies when they were young
were software companies. It wasn't until
they got like a lot even those guys the
best guys um needed some experience in
building a companies building technology
and so forth to kind of graduate to the
much more kind of complicated or
I would say elaborate domains you know
there's just much more there many more
moving parts in these things and so look
when you're learning how to build a
company it's hard enough if you
completely understand the product. If
you don't completely understand the
product and have to learn it while you
build the company, um that's just such a
steep learning curve for a brand new
entrepreneur. So, I think that what
we're seeing is you see Michael on the
one hand, um who is a very young guy,
brilliant, but what he built was kind of
a pure
software AI thing.
>> Yeah. And then on the other end, you
have like an Elon or a Travis who can
who's got enough experience. I think
Michael could probably do that, you
know, 10 years from now, but today that
would have been hard.
>> And it's important to remember like it's
been defocused by the entire industry
and academia for the last 20 years,
right? It just there just hasn't been
the same opportunity. Like it's been
there, but like it's never been a growth
area. The growth areas have been, you
know, software, um, networking, things
like that. And so I also think we just
have a posity of people coming out of
the universities or having experience at
large companies that have have done
this. I there just not that many.
>> Like you don't go intern and like build
a chip. So but a lot of that's changing
now. like listen we're going to create a
whole generation of of you know founders
that come from these new companies that
will know how to do this and you know
they'll be hired in much more junior and
like I would say actually one of the
greatest legacies of Elon towards this
is is of course he's created these great
companies but the amount of
entrepreneurs that have come out of
SpaceX that that have are changing the
entire industrial complex maybe even
greater um legacy than than the
companies themselves and I think we're
going to see the same thing uh for for
computer science and hardware
>> y as a matter of All of our investments
was started by uh two founders in their
20ies. But if you go watch one of their
offices, you see the experienced people
as well. So it's ideal combination here.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah. It doesn't necessarily have
to be the founder with experience, but
that founder better be able to tap into
that experience with it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well, and then be able to
work with them and and and
they have to be good and and all these
kinds of things. It's complicated.
Speaking of experience, this is a a big
new fund we're we're launching and
there's no new GPS. Um yeah, we're sort
of collecting. It's because you guys
have a lot of experience and the rest of
the group, you know, in in this field
that it's been kind of latent and uh
dormant. Yeah. Well, it's kind of funny.
I think we almost had to be warned
against it almost just because like our
backgrounds are from is hard. And I
think the reason that we needed a
reminder is because all of us have spent
so much in our careers existence and
hardware. We're kind of drawn to that.
And so listen, we've been clearly
invested
um in harbor over other years, right?
We're in SpaceX, we're in Andrew and
all. These are very early checks. We're
in astronomics, we're in Whimo, you
know, so we even even early on we did a
number of those investments. Um but like
you know this is because it's so much in
our DNA and so I don't think this is
necessarily need to increase the team
competencies just bonus.
>> If this fund does what we think it will
do,
>> how do we see the world changing or
looking like in 5 to 10 years? Well, you
know, hopefully uh America wins in the
infrastructure game. Um and we have lots
of like super eco-friendly efficient
data centers out there and lots and lots
an abundance of chips and abundance of
memory and abundance of power. Uh and
you know that would be awesome. Uh, and
I think we look we we, you know, it goes
back to like we really think uh America
is a special place and um we're
important not only to everybody here but
anybody in the world who wants to kind
of make a contribution and do something
bigger than themselves that it's kind of
the best place to come with nothing and
do something profound. So we'd like to
keep that going and I I think that
doesn't continue to go if we lose our
lead in technology. Think I think we'll
be in another era and it'll be another
country and maybe they have a different
set of values around that.
>> Thanks. That's a wrap.
>> Great for seeing me fun. Martine Beni.
Thank you. Thank you.
>> Thank you. Thanks. Yeah.